Guide to the Betsy Schreiber papers, 1897-1996 MS 796
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Betsy Schreiber Papers
1897-1996
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Schreiber, Elizabeth "Betsy"
MS 796
.50 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection includes correspondence, certificates, invitations, photographs, booklets, memorabilia and realia that documents Betsy Schreiber's family from 1897 to 1996.
Biographical / Historical
Annie Bleaden was the great grandmother of Betsy Marks Schreiber. She married Louis Silain in March, 1897. Louis changed the spelling of his last name to Seline. The couple lived in Houston and had four children – Hyman, Gertrude, Dora, and David. The four Seline children lived in Houston all of their lives and many of their descendants still do.
In 1928 Gertrude Seline, the oldest daughter, married Seymour Nathan. Gertrude was born in 1899 and Seymour was born in 1894. In 1930 they had twin daughters, Joanna and Nona Jane Nathan.
Nona Jane married Richard Marks in 1954 in Houston at Westwood Country Club. They had two children, Kenneth and Betsy. Kenneth married Elena Maslia Marks and they have three children, Andy, Elliot and Evan. Elliot is an MBA graduate of Rice's Jones School. Betsy married Edward Schreiber and they have two children, Jessica and Emily. Emily works at Rice University as the director of development for the southeastern region of the US.
Gertrude Nathan, born in 1899, set a goal of living in three centuries. When the year 2000 arrived she explained to all that 2000 was the final year of the previous century, not the first year of the new century. She died on September 1, 2001 having achieved her goal.
Scope and Contents
One box containing correspondence, certificates, invitations, photographs, booklets, memorabilia and realia documents Betsy Schreiber's family from 1897 to 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Elizabeth Shreiber donated the papers in January of 2018.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged into four series as follows:
Series I: Beth Israel; Series II: San Jacinto High School; Series III: Sigma Theta Pi; and Series IV: General
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; Social life and customs
Document Types
photographs; Ephemera; Records (documents)
Subjects (Persons)
Schreiber, Elizabeth "Betsy"
- Series I: Beth Israel
  - Certificate of Confirmation (Nora Jane Nathan), Congregation Beth Israel, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congregation Beth Israel Confirmation Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Congregation Beth Israel Programs, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: San Jacinto High School
  - San Jacinto High School baseball team photograph, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Biographical / Historical
    The photograph includes: Richard Marks (Betsy's father), Hershel Maltz, Eddie Sheinberg (sp), and Kenneth Schnitzer.
  - San Jacinto High School diploma (Betsy's mom, Nona Jane Nathan), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - San Jacinto High School Class of 1946 Reunion Photographs, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: Sigma Theta Pi
  - Sigma Theta Pi Booklets, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sigma Theta Pi pledge diary, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sigma Theta Pi Spring Formal Photographs, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sigma Theta Pi matches, c. 1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sigma Theta Pi sorority pin, c. 1970's (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sigma Theta Pi Napkin, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sigma Theta Pi Tea Party Invite, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series IV: General
  - Wedding invitations (2) - Annie Bleaden to Louis Silain (Betsy's great-grandparents), Houston; Gertrude Seline to Seymour Nathan (Betsy's grandparents), Houston, 1897-03-28-1928-01-03 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beth Israel - Chagall Temple Window Production, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sigma Alpha Rho Programs, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Confirmation Class Shavuot/Invitation, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Houston JCC Basketball Ticket, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Beth Yeshurun T.I.G.E.R.S. Letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Holocaust Education and Service Packets (Box 1, Folder 20)